There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at some of the
ways to reduce wrinkles.
And we start with a look
at the safety and efficacy
of botox injections
and facelift surgery.
Anti-aging medicine
is one of the fastest growing
medical specialties,
and often targeted at women,
who are urged to restore
their youthful appearance
by "any and all
available means."
This includes surgery.
92 percent
of cosmetic procedures
are performed on women,
most commonly Botox, fillers,
and laser or chemical
peel skin resurfacing,
but millions in the U.S. undergo
cosmetic surgery every year,
including hundreds of thousands
of face-lifts.
There's no consensus on
the best face-lift technique.
None have been shown to be
definitively better than others.
A systematic review found that
most of the studies
on the newest techniques
were mere case series,
one of the lowest levels
on the hierarchy of evidence,
basically composed of a string
of glorified anecdotes.
According to one of the largest
and most up-to-date analyses,
face-lifts are considered
relatively safe when performed
by a board-certified
plastic surgeon,
with surgical complications
only happening
in about 1 in 20 cases,
most often hematomas,
where blood collects
under the skin flaps,
or minor infections.
Serious infections,
like facial necrotizing
fasciitis
caused by flesh-eating bacteria
are rare,
as is pyoderma gangrenosum,
a disfiguring, skin ulcerating
autoimmune disease
that can be triggered
by face-lift surgery.
Nerve injuries occur in at most
a few percent of cases,
but only about
1 in 1000 procedures
may result in permanent
facial nerve injury.
About two-thirds of face-lifts
are performed under
general anesthesia,
which is associated with
a greater risk of complications.
The most important way
to mediate risk
is to refrain from smoking.
Smoking can increase the risk
of skin flap necrosis,
or tissue death,
up to twenty-fold.
Patients should refrain from
smoking at least a month before
and month after surgery.
Tempering expectations
is also important.
Approximately 1 in 3 women
experience a period
of postoperative depression,
but this may just be
in reaction to
the temporary distortion
and discoloration
of swelling and bruising
after surgery.
The most profitable
cosmetic procedure is Botox,
in the billions,
as well as the most common,
performed more than four million
times a year in the US alone.
It all started when
a group of surgeons noticed
that patients with Bell's palsy,
facial paralysis,
didn't have as many wrinkles.
So what about
injecting minute amounts
of the nerve-blocking toxin
that causes botulism
to paralyze a few
facial muscles on purpose,
and a multibillion-dollar
industry was born.
The effect is temporary,
typically lasting
three to four months
until the body can grow back
new nerve terminals.
In response to cases of
respiratory failure and death
occurring hours or even weeks
after injection,
in 2009 the FDA mandated
a black box warning
regarding the potential
spread of the toxin
resulting in death
from swallowing
and breathing difficulties
occurring hours, days,
or weeks after injection.
However, most of these
complications were tied
not to cosmetic uses
but to treating muscle spasms--
for example in cerebral palsy.
For wrinkles, only 30 to 60
units of the toxin may be used,
compared to an average of about
180 for severe muscle spasms,
though still a far cry
from the estimated lethal dose
of perhaps 3,000 units.
The dose is given in MU,
"mouse units,"
with one MU being the amount
capable of poisoning
half of a group
of albino mice to death.
In studies, less than
1 in 2,000 Botox procedures
resulted in complications,
which can include droopy
eyelids, double vision,
an asymmetrical smile,
or the Spock,
a devilish curvature of
the outer portion of the brow.
Unfortunately, not all such
procedures are performed
under such
controlled conditions.
In many states,
there is surprisingly little
or no regulation
as to who can deliver Botox,
leading to a rapid increase
in injections
by nonmedical personnel.
In one five-ish year period,
about 30,000 complications
allegedly tied to Botox
were reported to the FDA,
most commonly pain, swelling,
and eyelid or eyebrow drooping,
but most adverse effects are
transient and self-limited.
In our next story,
almonds are put to the test in a randomized
controlled trial for facial wrinkles.
After my video on dates
blew my mind, showing that
eating just a few dates
can significantly reduce
the duration of labor
during childbirth and
improve the progression of labor.
But there are some surprising
benefits attributed to nuts
in randomized controlled
trials, like how about a study
on the effects of almond
consumption on wrinkles?
Where’d they even
come up with the idea?
Well, population studies
have found that healthy diets
are associated with
less facial wrinkles,
like a meat and junk-
predominant eating pattern
was associated with
more wrinkles, whereas
a fruit-predominant pattern was
associated with fewer wrinkles.
In terms of single foods,
yellow vegetables and soy
appear protective, but
wine may make things worse.
Their thinking is that it
might be the antioxidants
in healthy foods decreasing
the oxidative stress load,
or the anti-inflammatory benefits,
or protection from sun damage,
or improved collagen production,
or better DNA repair.
I have videos on most
of those topics.
The bottom line is
that eating healthier
may reduce wrinkling, which
could actually save lives
if people started eating healthier
to maintain a more youthful
appearance and get all
the chronic disease benefits
as a happy side effect.
Other studies have found the same
thing, supporting recommendations
for more healthy foods like
fruits, vegetables, and nuts.
Here’s another
study that landed on
yellow vegetables,
and greens as well.
In this study, a high intake of
vegetables, beans, and olive oil
appeared to be protective against
spots of precancerous
sun damage,
whereas a high intake of meat
and dairy may make things worse.
Prunes, apples, and tea
seemed particularly good,
but this was a
cross-sectional study,
meaning just a snapshot in time.
Maybe people who eat more meat
are out barbequing in the sun,
or people who eat more prunes
just use more sunblock.
You can’t know for sure if
foods actually affect wrinkling
until you... put them to the test—
but we had no such
studies…until, now.
Why study almonds?
Because it was paid for by
the Almond Board, of course.
The researchers didn’t know
who was in the nut group, though,
and who was in
the control group,
until they were
looking at the results.
The nut group were given
2 ounces of nuts a day,
like two palmfuls of nuts, and
the control group was instead
given nut-free snacks
to eat instead
like nut-free granola
bars or pretzels.
Before and after, they got
high‐res facial photographs
to quantify facial wrinkle
depth and severity using
a computer‐based photographic
analysis and…boom,
the almond group had significantly
decreased wrinkle severity
compared with the control group
by the end of the 16-week study.
The paper concludes:
“Our study demonstrates that
daily almond consumption
may reduce wrinkle severity...”
Now, they used a relatively
large dose, 2 ounces a day,
whereas you can get
cardioprotective benefits
of nuts from even less
than a half an ounce;
so, who knows, maybe they could
have gotten away with using less.
Here’s the low-dose nut
study they referenced,
showing a significant drop in
LDL cholesterol within 6 weeks
eating just a few
almonds a day—10 grams
which is just like
8 almonds a day.
That’s the nice thing
about healthy foods,
they just have good
side effects.
So, global disease prevention
strategies might beneﬁt
from emphasizing that a
healthy diet is also linked
to less facial wrinkling,
and maybe vanity will help us
prevent a few heart
attacks in the bargain.
Finally today,
did you know that the skin folding
caused by everyday facial expressions
etches once-temporary grooves
into permanent wrinkles,
but only in the context of
underlying structural damage.
How are wrinkles formed?
Their origin and nature is said
to be "notoriously complex,"
but current thinking
is that wrinkles occur
where fault lines
develop in aging skin.
The process has been compared
to an old leather glove,
made out of skin after all,
that develops creases
at the joints
due to repetitive stress.
In the face,
the repeated flexion
may be due
to facial expression.
An 8-year longitudinal study
found that you can predict
the pattern
of persistent wrinkles
by superimposing
upon your resting face
the expression lines,
temporary wrinkles,
that form when you smile.
Over time,
the skin folding
caused by
everyday facial expressions
etches the temporary grooves
into permanent wrinkles.
Given that wrinkles develop
from forehead furrows
and expression lines
from frowns and laughter,
one dermatology journal review
on aging skin
offered the tongue in
unwrinkled-cheek suggestion
of "Living alone to minimize
the use of facial expressions."
And while you're at it
you could
"live in space to avoid
the effects of gravity."
However, there is a way
to freeze parts of your face
into an expressionless mask:
Botox.
In fact, one contraindication
to getting Botox
is having a job that
"necessitates a wide range
of facial expressions."
It's never been
formally put to the test,
but there was a case report
of a pair of identical twins,
one of whom who spent
tens of thousands of dollars
getting Botox treatments across
multiple areas on her face
a few times each year
for 13 years.
Compared to her
non-regularly injected twin,
she ended up with
fewer imprinted facial lines.
A paper entitled
"Sleep Wrinkles"
tried to make the case
that wrinkles may result
from the skin distortion
from mechanical compression
sleeping on your side.
Of course, the primary author
also is a partner in a company
selling $160 quote-unquote
"wrinkle-fighting" pillows.
It turns out there does not
appear to be any correlation
between sleep position
preference
and the appearance of wrinkles.
Speaking of
questionable products,
what about topical adhesive
"anti-wrinkle" pads
you paste to your face at night?
Product claims include "look up
to 10-15 years younger,"
declaring a 70 percent reduction
in wrinkles.
But when actually
put to the test for a month
for crow's feet, forehead,
or between-the-eye wrinkles,
no objective benefits
were reported at all.
There did appear to be a placebo
effect in that subjectively,
the study participants felt
the wrinkles looked better,
but independent
blinded evaluations
by facial plastic surgeons
of before-and-after pictures
showed no significant change.
So what can we do
to prevent wrinkling?
Some of it is genetics.
For example, having lighter skin
color is a predisposing factor.
Among light skin tones,
Caucasian skin wrinkles more
readily than Asian skin,
for which aging
is more characterized
by pigmentation changes
such as freckles, blotchy
patches, and liver spots.
Among Asian skin types,
Chinese women tend to have
more wrinkles around their eyes
than Japanese women,
whereas Thai women
tend to wrinkle more
in the lower half
of their faces.
There are, however,
factors we have control over.
For example, drier skin has
also been found predictive
of more persistent wrinkling,
suggesting regular use
of skin moisturizers may help.
When it comes
to wrinkle formation,
it takes two to tango.
Wrinkles are formed
by repetitive creasing
of aged skin.
Kids can scrunch their faces
all they want
because the architecture
of their skin has yet to be
irreparably damaged,
and the lack of creasing
is why you don't have
wrinkles on your forearms
no matter how much sun
they've soaked up.
Rather than immobilizing
your face with Botox,
you can focus on preventing
the underlying structural damage
that makes your skin
susceptible.
This involves tobacco avoidance
and regular sun protection.
What about safeguarding
against other kinds of light?
From the Journal of Biomedical
Physics and Engineering:
"Can light emitted
from smartphone screens
and taking selfies cause
premature aging and wrinkles?"
Human skin cells bathed in
the light of iPhones and iPads
experienced an 80 to 90 percent
increase in free radicals,
compared to shielded
control cells,
suggesting electronic device
generated light
"may be harmful to skin."
Now, on one hand,
they positioned the screens
unrealistically close,
one centimeter,
resulting in about
10 times the irradiance
compared to a reading distance
of about a foot.
On the other hand,
the skin cells were only exposed
for an unrealistically
short time, only an hour.
The researchers called
for future studies
to evaluate the impact
of lower, longer doses
on skin outcomes
such as collagen deposition.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.